A Guide to the Papers of John Powell, 1888-1978, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series IV: Eugenics and Racial Integrity
  - C. Correspondence concerning Eugenics: Plecker
    - Letter read by the Honorable Albert O. Boschen during the interview of William Archer Thaddeus Jones, January 3, 1925; December 1, 1910, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:29)
      Two letters are typed onto the same page regarding the racial status of Mrs. Emma Jones. One letter, dated December 1, 1910 is from G. M. Cook to Chief William O. Adkins and the second letter, dated January 27, 1925 is from Clarence Jennings, Superintendent of Schools to the Honorable O. Boschen.
    - W.A. Plecker to Leon Adler, Sales Manager, National Motion Pictures Co., Indianapolis, February 9, 1925, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:30)
      Plecker suggests that Louise Powell and Adler could work together on a film about racial integrity. Adler made a non-inflammable film, The Error of Omission and also a film called In His Father's Footsteps.
    - W.A. Plecker to the Honorable George H. Roberts, Ohio, February 25, 1925, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:31)
      Plecker writes about Ohio legislation that forbids the intermarriage of the races and would appreciate being kept advised of its progress. Plecker also writes that he is very impressed with the phrase "or have carnal knowledge" that Roberts uses in his bill. Plecker may use it in his next amendment.
    - "Statement of D. F. Rudisill, local registrar at Roxbury to ?ill Adkins," February 1925, 1 TL, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:32)
      "Mr. D. F. Rudisill, local registrar at Roxbury, gives us Hill Adkins' Reason for not Joining the 'Tribe.'" Rudisill states that Adkins could have been in the Indian tribe if he desired but he claimed he did not have the money to "throw away" on membership fees. He said, "I am a negro and stay with the negroes."
    - "Stenographic Report of an Interview Regarding 'the so-called Indians' of Charles City County" between Mr. E. H. Marston and Dr. W. A. Plecker, February 1925, TM, 5 pp. (Box-folder 41:33)
    - W. A. Plecker to Senator Morris Sheppard, March 12, 1925, TLS, 1 p (Box-folder 41:34)
      Sheppard requests Plecker to write a racial integrity bill for the District of Columbia, and Plecker recommends C. H. Morrissett, Director Legislative Reference Bureau who wrote a good bill for Ohio. Plecker also mentions that Homer Ferguson, the head of the great ship-building plant of Newport News, strongly advocates writing an amendment that covers the point of extra-marital intercourse between the races.
    - W.A. Plecker to the Editor, Survey Graphic, March 13, 1925, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:35)
      Plecker writes in response to a magazine article that attacks racial integrity legislation. He counters that he has great affection for Negroes but that does not mean they would tolerate marriage with them.
    - W.A. Plecker to Homer N. Calver, Executive Secretary, American Public Health Association, March 17, 1925, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:36)
      Plecker has written a paper on immigration and sends it to Calver. He discusses the criticism that he received on it from Richard L. Jenkins, Stanford University. Plecker suspects the criticism is coming from a Negro and not from Stanford University faculty. Plecker feels that his paper is very conservative in comparison with A. E. Wiggam's Fruit of the Family Tree.
    - W. A. Plecker to the Honorable H.W. Urquhart, March 17, 1925, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:37)
      Plecker shares information about racial integrity legislation in order to help Massachusetts with similar legislation. He points out certain defects in the law and advises him to improve it.
    - W. A. Plecker to Marion S. Alley, April 15, 1925, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:38)
      Plecker helps Alley with racial integrity legislation for the District of Columbia. Plecker ask if Congressman J. L. Milligan supports the bill to prevent the intermarriage of the races in the District of Columbia which Senator Sheppard of Texas will introduce at the next Congress. He also writes about the organization of Anglo-Saxon clubs and refers him to John Powell and Dr. Lawrence Price.
    - W.A. Plecker to the Honorable Stone Deavours, Mississippi, April 15, 1925, 1 TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:39)
      Plecker appreciates Devours' support against racial intermarriage and complains about the New York Association for the Improvement of the Colored Race, and the negro newspapers throughout the country. Plecker writes that he did not realize that the negroes were so "bitter" and "determined to pass as white." Plecker thinks that with legislation they can delay amalgamation for five hundred years instead of two hundred.
    - W.A. Plecker to D. Harrower, April 27, 1925, TLS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 41:40)
      Plecker explains that "for any person therefore, to claim to be an Indian, so as to be eligible for inter-marriage with whites, it is necessary for him to show that there has never been any introduction of negro blood into his family." Plecker mentions that the Pamunkeys, Rappahannocks, Amherst Rockbridge group and the Chickahominies are part Negro. He also cites Estabrook's findings that Negroes have a low mentality and a high rate of illegitimacy. He mentions that William Archer Jones fails the "comb test." He hopes that the next legislature will repeal the one-sixteenth Indian clause from the law.
    - W. A. Plecker to John Powell, April 27, 1925, TLS, 1 pp. (Box-folder 41:41)
      Plecker supports the possibility of C. E. McKenry being appointed by the Governor as a member of the commission that confers with other states on the uniformity of legislation. He also writes a that Harrower is pleading that, "I be fair to these most admirable people." Plecker hopes that they have stopped the issuing of Speck's report and asks Powell "to call upon the Indian Museum people and tell them a few things. George Heyer is the active man with Harrower."
    - W.A. Plecker to Editor, The Richmond Times-Dispatch, April 28, 1925, 1 TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:42)
      Plecker complains that the article about an Indian reservation is inaccurate and romanticized, which leads people to believe that it is okay to intermarry with mixed races. He writes that he has studied the records as far back as 1853 and these people are no longer Indian. He writes, "History and the United States Bureau of Ethnology speak in no uncertain tones. That Bureau in a number of references to the Pamunkeys, Chickahominies, Mattaponis and Croatons describe them as being mixed with negro and white." He cites Howe's, History of Virginia (1845) as his reference. Plecker also writes about the "fish-fries" that white women are attending and wants them to be stopped.
    - W. A. Plecker to John K. Gailey, March 21, 1925, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:43)
      Plecker answers Gaileys' questions regarding Plecker's paper. He recommends that Gailey read a pamphlet by A. H. Shannon and the book, White America. He also describes how the Negroes are inferior and claims that they were at their intellectual peak before the Civil War when they were obedient.
    - W.A. Plecker to Thomas L. Dabney, July 7, 1925, TLS, 3 pp. (Box-folder 41:44)
      Plecker replies to his questions about the Garvey movement by writing that he believes Garvey's courage and leadership will bring success to the movement for the first time since Lincoln. Plecker recommends that Dabney read Cox's Let My People Go and White America.
    - W.A. Plecker to the Reverend Arthur P. Gray, March 2, 1926, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:45)
      Plecker gives John Powell a message to contact Gray. Plecker writes that he would be glad to have Gray visit and work with him on "the great task of preserving the integrity of the races."
    - W.A. Plecker to Senator Griswold Webb, March 3, 1926, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:46)
      Plecker offers advice on racial integrity legislation and warns him that "the registration part of the Act is a failure because the near-white undesirables are using it to attempt to register as white." He writes that there is a new bill which is set for a hearing in the House tomorrow. He also warns that the Association for the Improvement of the Colored Race will oppose it. Plecker offers assistance from Madison Grant, Lothrop Stoddard, Dr. Charles B. Davenport, and himself.
    - Amherst Registrar to W. A to Plecker, March 10, 1926, TLS, 4 pp. (Box-folder 41:47)
      The Amherst registrar has spoken with Mr. Ambler as Plecker suggested and now, the registrar has the history of the Amherst issues. The history is from Howe's History of Virginia and a record of the lineage of some of the "issues."
    - W. A. Plecker to the President of the United States, March 19, 1927, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:48)
      Plecker pleads to the President in support of a pardon for Marcus Garvey. He writes, "I am one of a considerable number of white people of Virginia who have given his case thought, and who believe that his violation of the law was an error of judgment rather than deliberate crime. Believing that he has been imprisoned sufficiently long to serve the ends of justice, I plead in his behalf that he may be pardoned, and permitted to continue his work with his race in this country."
    - W.A. Plecker to John Powell, March 19, 1927, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:49)
      Plecker writes that he received a letter from Amy Garvey saying that there would be an application to the President for the pardon of her husband, Marcus Garvey. Plecker and Earnest S. Cox have written the President and encourage Powell to write. Plecker writes that George Mallison, of Hampton may also write a letter.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Augusta B. Fothergill, January 21, 1928, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:50)
      Plecker asks about her health and mentions that his own wife has been sick for nearly a year with a complete nervous breakdown. He writes that he will send the Colonial Dames literature on racial integrity laws. He also explains the bills definition of an Indian as one with 1/4 Indian blood. He mentions that "the present law was not repealed which allows a mulatto of 1/16 or more negro blood and the rest white to be classed as white."
    - W.A. Plecker to Clerk, House of Delegates, Jackson, Mississippi, February 15, 1928, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:51)
      Plecker offers his assistance with their racial integrity legislation. He would like to know who introduced the bill and to have a copy of it and a printed list of the members of the legislature. He writes that he hopes that they do not copy the mistakes in the Virginia law, especially the registration, which coloreds are using to pass as Indians. He mentions that Alabama has a good law but Georgia copied the mistakes of Virginia.
    - W. A. Plecker to the Tower Press, November 3, 1930, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:52)
      Plecker writes that Anglo-Saxon clubs were set up to help the passage of racial integrity laws and are not currently active. He refers them to John Powell for further information.
    - W. A. Plecker to the Honorable W. M. Steuart, Director of the U.S. Bureau of the Census, August 4, 1931, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:53)
      Plecker advises him of the mulattoes who are registering as Indian. He sends Steuart a copy of a letter from the Honorable A. D. Latane, Clerk of Essex County who can identify the mulattoes. Plecker emphasizes that this group "should under no circumstances be given classification as Indians in the census records."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. John Powell, September 3, 1931, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:54)
      Plecker writes that he is delighted with the emphatic manner in which John Powell presented the matter to Mr. Steuart in his letter. Mr Steuart "seems perfectly willing to do what is right and to act upon it."
    - W. A. Plecker to John Powell, June 7, 1933, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:55)
      Plecker writes about a Mrs. Trigg who is planning an exhibit in the Valentine Museum on Indians and she thinks that there are hundreds of them in Virginia. He writes, "The lady was greatly surprised when I told her that there were no native born Indians in the State." He complains about the publicity of Indians and thinks that Powell could stop it. He also mentions Mrs. Fothergill, a genealogist, who has information on the racial origin of the Pamunkeys and Mattaponies.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Howard H. Sorrell, former local registrar of Amherst County, March 9, 1934, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:56)
      Plecker writes that he has heard Sorrell's theory about the descendants of Cain and is not interested in the subject. Plecker states that he does want to know more about the families of the Beverlys, Weavers, Johns, and Clarks who live near the Sorrells. He writes that he did not know that they were establishing another colony.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. L. Quibell, March 10, 1934, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:57)
      Plecker writes that his office has "secured definite information " on the racial status of Clarence Brown of Buckingham County as a Negro. He writes, "You have the thing straight now, and we hope that your daughter can see the seriousness of the whole matter and will dismiss this young man without more ado. We will be glad to have you advise us as to the outcome of the whole matter."
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss Lizzie Ware, October 2, 1935, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:58)
      Plecker writes that they have received her inquiry as to the racial standing of the children of Mrs. Warren Odgen. Plecker also writes, "Please tell me just what the appearance of this woman, her husband and children is. Do any of the family have any negro characteristics. Frequently these show in one member of the family and not in another."
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss Grace Davison, October 4, 1935, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:59)
      Plecker writes that the racial classification of a native Filipino is classed as colored as well as all Asiatics, including Chinese, Japanese, native of India, etc. Under the law of Virginia, they are not permitted to marry white people and their child will be classed as colored.
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss Elizabeth Tyler, April 16, 1936, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:60)
      Plecker writes that he received her letter requesting the names of the negroes living on the Indian reservations and questions her reasons for wanting this information. He explains the history of the Indians, and the politics involved in reclassifying these people from Negro to Indian in 1902. He also writes about the petition of 1843 where citizens of King William County asked the legislature to abolish the reservations because the occupants were no longer Indians. Plecker states, "If you write again, I shall be glad to have you tell us your purpose in asking for this information." He also mentions the famous "fish-fry " in Charles City County, which encourages inter-racial mixing.
    - W.A. Plecker to Mrs. A. P. Bohannon, May 3, 1938, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:61)
      Plecker explains the proper terms to use when registering people. He emphasizes that there is no mixed-Indian and advises her not to let them intimidate her into using that term. He advises her that registrars do not recognize any native born people of Virginia who call themselves Indians. He does admit that there is a man in Lexington, Virginia who is one-fourth Indian, and three-fourths white.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. J. J. Ambler-Amherst, May 27, 1938, TLS, 2pp. and enclosure. (Box-folder 41:61)
      Plecker writes that Samuel Christian Branham is perjuring himself when he claims that he is white on his application to marry Grace Vernon Mohler.
    - W. A. Plecker to E. B. Ford, Esq. the Honorable Scientific Secretary Bureau of Human Heredity, March 22, 1939, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:62)
      Plecker writes to Ford about the tasks of the Bureau of Vital Statistics and their serious efforts to prevent further amalgamation which is only being done in Virginia. He explains that they use birth, death and marriage records, U. S Census records, and military records in accordance with the Act of 1924 to determine the accurate racial status of residents of Virginia. Plecker also sends him literature, such as a reprint of The Breach in the Dike by John Powell and other books by Earnest Sevier Cox. He also mentions Senator Bilbo of Mississippi, who is preparing to introduce a bill to the Senate that supports the deportation of Negroes.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Hale Collins, Attorney, Covington, Virginia, April 3, 1939, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:63)
      Plecker encloses the certified copy, as requested, of the marriage record of Calvin Branham and Birdie Johns and the marriage record of Wilmer K. Marshall (all colored) and Catherine V. Johns who swears that she is white while Plecker states that this is incorrect.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mrs. Mary L. Martin, April 11, 1939, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:64)
      Plecker writes that his office needs Thomas Earnest Sorrells and Elizabeth Martin to fill out the questionnaire giving their background. He writes that their child Priscilla June Sorrells cannot be classed as white until there is evidence that neither of her parents are of mixed blood.
    - W.A. Plecker to Mr. Wilton H. Lehr, Virginia Polytechnical Institute, April 25, 1939, TLS. (Box-folder 41:65)
      Plecker responds that his office does not have enough funding to perform the necessary research needed to answer Lehr's request concerning the racial status of certain individuals. He refers him to Dr. Garnett "who is doing a very splendid piece of work in studying sub-marginal people..." Plecker is very interested in what information Lehr has collected concerning mixed families. He offers his records as long as the source is kept confidential.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. L. H. Shrader, May 10, 1939, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:66)
      Plecker writes Mr. Shrader asking for information about a name change of Beverly to Burch for "a free issue " in Amherst County.
    - W. A. Plecker to Senator Robert Reynolds, May 17, 1939, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:67)
      Plecker congratulates him on his speech in reference to "refusing admittance into this country of German refugees." He would be glad to send him racial integrity literature. He also commends Senator Bilbo on his speech.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Roy K. Brown, Clerk, Roanoke County, May 17, 1939, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:68)
      Plecker writes about a marriage between Dalbert Charlie Maxey (age 21) and Mary Magdalene Crum (age 16) and asks the clerk if he noticed if Mr. Maxey has mulatto characteristics. Plecker writes, "Shall this man, if he is of the Amherst group, be turned loose upon the community to raise more mulatto children?"
    - W. A. Plecker to H. D. Kissenger, Missouri, May 17, 1939, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:69)
      Plecker gives a background history on the Virginia Racial Integrity legislation and offers his assistance for similar legislation in Missouri.
    - W. A. Plecker to the Reverend G. W. Headen, May 17, 1939, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:70)
      Plecker writes, "We are enclosing a copy of our letter to Mr. Roy K. Brown, Clerk of Roanoke County. Did you observe any negro characteristics in this man? It is possible for a couple of this kind to get by the clerk and yet be held up by the minister. If this man comes from the family that we think he did, this marriage is illegal."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. V. W. Nichols, Clerk Circuit Court Bedford County, May 19, 1939, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:71)
      Plecker writes that he has received Mr. Nichols' inquiry on the racial status of Dalbert Charlie Maxey who appears to be of mixed blood. Plecker responds that they need more information on Maxey and is sending questionnaires for Maxey to fill out.
    - W. A. Plecker to Dr. David W. Peters, President State Teachers College, April 17, 1940, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:72)
      Plecker considers Peters question about whether Indians are barred from enrolling in white state schools. He writes that he does not know the answer as the Attorney General has not ruled on it but he thinks it would be safer to avoid establishing a precedent.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. G. B. Wallace, April 20, 1940, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:73)
      Plecker writes that his office does not have any information on the birth of Lillian Cunningham of King George County born in the year 1913 or 1914 because they do not have records of births between 1896 and 1912.
    - W. A. Plecker writes to Mr. William E. Sandidge, Clerk, Amherst, April 20, 1940, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:74)
      Plecker writes that the records of his office are insufficient to establish the racial status of Jesse Sorrells who has applied for a marriage license to marry a white girl.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. William E. Sandidge, April 24, 1940, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:75)
      Plecker writes that his office has received a request from the sister of Jesse Sorrells for a birth certificate so that she can be admitted into a training school for nurses.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. L. B. Mason, Clerk, King George County Circuit Court, May 14, 1940, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:76)
      Plecker answers Mason's inquiry by saying that their records show that Lillian Pearl Cunningham is listed as white on her marriage license but the Cunningham family is a mulatto family in Virginia trying to pass as white. He cites as evidence the census report of 1870.
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Elmer Hunt, June 11, 1940, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:77)
      Plecker writes that he is returning Hunt's birth certificate because red is not an acceptable racial term. He also writes that the Hunt and Locklear families have been proven to be of "negro origin."
    - W. A. Plecker to Miss Blanche Cunningham, June 11, 1940, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:78)
      Plecker writes that he is surprised that one of the respectable Cunningham family would be asking about the racial status of Gus Stewart's children. Plecker writes that he was present when one of the Stewart children was born and recorded as "Indian and colored." Plecker writes, "I trust that...you will immediately break off entirely with this young mulatto man."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. C. K. Holsinger, Superintendent, Henrico County Public Schools, June 11, 1940, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:79)
      In response to Holsinger's inquiries, Plecker writes that the father of these children is a white man but the mother "is of free negro descent." Plecker writes, "This family has been especially aggressive in their endeavors to secure classification as white. The fact that the mother secured admittance in to the white ward of Memorial Hospital is evidence of this fact."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. Marvin Gregg, June 13, 1940, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:80)
      Plecker writes, "You asked us to look up the ancestry of Juan F. Johns and let you know if there is any negro blood. You do not tell us who you are or why you are asking that question, which we must know before we can give you any information about this man. You did not tell us where he came from or who his parents and grandparents were, which is necessary if we are to examine our records."
    - W. A. Plecker to Mr. R. I. Overbey, Attorney, Rustburg, Virginia, July 11, 1940, 1 TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 41:81)
      Plecker writes that his office would be glad to give all the assistance possible in securing the correct classification of the children and he would like to get all of the information on their parentage.
    - W. A. Plecker to Dr. H. V. Fitzgerald, Chairman, Chatham County School Board, July 11, 1940, TLS, 2 pp. (Box-folder 41:82)